Good morning everyone.
Today is Friday, March 16th, the 29th of אדר, Adar, and today's
דף Daf will be עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, דף סמך, Daf Samech,
and
we will start from
the
third to last line of נ"ט עמוד ב. Nun Tet Amud Bet.
We're continuing along with some of these sort of short סוגיות Sugyot
with some kind of a case that presented itself to the אמוראים
Amora'im and then they gave their פסק Psak and then some of
the details get worked out along the way. So the גמרא Gemara
says ההיא חביתא דחמרא דאשתקיל ברזא: Ha-hi chavita d'chamra d'ishtakil barza: there
was a barrel of, hopefully I can draw this kind now. The
problem is what kind of barrel are we talking about? Let's assume
for simplicity's sake it's just something like this, but and it has
a spout partially, partially here, right? Okay, didn't have fancy spouts like
this back then, but something like this. So now what happens? The
spout gets taken out. Now you just have a hole. What happens
when you have a hole in a barrel?
The wine starts coming out,
okay. Guy comes over and he's going to put his hands over
the over the thing to keep the wine coming out, okay. Non-Jew.
ההיא חביתא דחמרא דאשתקיל ברזא אתא עובד כוכבים אדרי אנח ידיה עלוי.
Ha-hi chavita d'chamra d'ishtakil barza ata oved kochavim idrei anach
yadei iloy. So the spout fell out, so the non-Jewish person comes
over and puts his hand over the hole to keep the wine
from spilling out. אמר רב פפא: Amar Rav Papa: כל דלהוי ברזא,
Kol de-lehavi barza, so everything that was sort of touching the spout
somewhere in the proximity of the spout area, whether it's the wine
that's here, whether it's the wine that already came out, okay,
אסור, Assur, that wine is prohibited because the non-Jewish person touched it,
ואידך שרי, Ve-idach shari, and the rest of the wine in the
whole barrel is permissible.
Okay, ואיכא דאמרי, Ve-ikka de'amri, second version of רב פפא, Rav Papa,
אמר רב פפא: Amar Rav Papa: עד הברזא חמרא אסור, Ad ha-barza
chamra assur, all of the wine in the top half of the
barrel
is
prohibited because it would have drained out of the hole, so the
fact that it remains in the barrel because this person holding their
hand against the spout is what keeps it in, so that's prohibited,
ואידך שרי, Ve-idach shari, and the part in the bottom half is
permissible. Okay, so one is obviously much more מחמיר Machmir than the
other. The first version of רב פפא Rav Papa basically says only
the wine in direct proximity to the opening is what's prohibited, but
the second version of רב פפא Rav Papa says anything that would
have been drained out of the barrel. Okay,
so אמר רב יימר: Amar Rav Yeimar: כתנאי, Ke'tannai, maybe this position
of רב פפא Rav Papa is associated with a מחלוקת תנאים Machloket
Tannaim and in fact רב פפא's Rav Papa position is that of
the minority position, as רש"י Rashi explains,
second second line of רש"י Rashi on סמך עמוד
א,
Samech
Amud Aleph, דהא דמוקי רב יימר מילתיה דרב פפא כתנאי וקאי ליה
רב פפא כרבי יהודה דיחידה היא:
De-ha de-moki Rav Yeimar miltei de'Rav Papa ke-tannai ve'kamlei Rav Papa ke'Rabbi
Yehuda de-yechida hi: so יחיד ורבים הלכה כרבים, Yachid ve-rabbim halacha ke-rabbim,
that actually רב פפא's Rav Papa position, the case that we just
discussed, is actually going to be associated with position of רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda and therefore רב יימר Rav Yeimar is challenging רב פפא
Rav Papa by saying oh, it's כתנאי Ke'tannai and your position is
like actually the minority position. So let's see what he says. It's
like this case from מסכת טבול יום, Masechet Tevul Yom, כתנאי, Ke'tannai,
the משנה Mishna in טבול יום Tevul Yom says חבית שנקבה, Chavita
she-nikba, a barrel that was pierced, that a hole, the hole, now
again, these barrels רש"י Rashi points out as well, here we're talking
about clay or pottery type of vessels, we're not talking about a
wooden barrel like was common already in רש"י's Rashi time.
Okay, so חבית שנקבה ובין מפיה בין משוליה, Chavit she-nikba u-vein mi-piha
bein mi-shuleha, if it was pierced in the מפיה Mi-piha at the
at the mouth at the opening of the barrel or on the
משוליה Shuleha on the underside of the barrel, ובין מצידיה, U-vein mi-tzideha,
or in the side, ונגע בו טבול יום, Ve-naga bo tevul yom,
טמאה, Tameia, and a טבול יום, Tevul Yom, someone who is still
טמא, Tamei, that is someone who has gone to the מקווה Mikvah
but still has to wait until sunset so he's considered to be
שני לטומאה, Sheni l'tumah, so if he touches the wine, טמאה, Tameia,
so we have to be talking about תרומה Terumah wine in order
for this to be a problem, okay. רבי יהודה אומר מפיה ומשוליה
טמאה, Rabbi Yehuda Omer mi-piha u-mi-shuleha tameia, if it's from the mouth
of the barrel or from the underside it will be prohibited. So
what the case we're talking about here, right, we're comparing: was the
hole at the top, at the bottom, or on the side, okay?
So רבי יהודה אומר מפיה ומשוליה
טמאה ומצידיה טהורה מכאן ומכאן,
Rabbi Yehuda omer mi-piha u-mi-shuleha tameia u-mi-tzideha
tehorah mikan u-mikan, if it
you the hole that it could drain out of is in the
top or in the bottom, then that's going to make The wine
in the whole barrel טמא, tamei, but if it was on the
side, it's not. So let's look at what רש״י Rashi says. So
רש״י Rashi says נקבה, nikva, yeah, it's the one נקבה מפיה הואיל
וכל היין שלמטה נעשה בסיס לעליון הוי חיבור ומשוליה נמי
הואיל וכל היין נמשך אחר הנקב הוי חיבור אבל נקב מצדיה טהורה
מכאן ומכאן.
nikva mi-pi-ha ho-il ve-chol ha-yayin she-lemata na'asa basis le-elyon havei chibbur u-mishuleha
nami ho-il ve-chol ha-yayin nimshach achar ha-nekev havei chibbur aval nekev mi-tzideha
tehorah mi-kan
u-mi-kan. So the point of רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda position, if the
hole is at the top, well then whatever you touch here, right,
the wine that he actually contacts is only up here, but the
rest of this is a בסיס, basis, it supports the wine. It's
what made it possible for him to touch this wine, so that
also is becomes associated at least for the laws of טומאה, tumah,
that if it's a בסיס, basis, it becomes the support. The lower
wine supports the wine on the top layer. Obviously, if you touch
the wine at the bottom, it's because all of the wine will
be able to drain out of the hole. And then if you
touch on the side, neither of those two really apply. Okay? Or
at least you would say only מכאן ומכאן mi-kan u-mi-kan like that
the amount above will be טמא tamei but everything underneath will be
טהור. tahor.
That's really strange.
It's a bit strange that he says from top and bottom are
both problematic and the side is less so.
Yeah, the side is like a line along the חבית. chavit.
We're going to see. It seems like he just means like a
hole in the side, like someone, you know, drilled a hole into
the, into the pot, into the earthenware. Part of the thing here
is some of these were made with, I would think all of
these were made with fired pottery, but the pottery was often relatively
thin so that you'd be able to puncture it to get the
wine out or whatever. A lot of the מלאכות שבת melachot Shabbat
that we have about, you know, soda cans and tuna cans and
things like that go back to these kinds of questions of containers
that were made in such a way that, you know, the neck
of the wine barrel would be very narrow and you would kind
of chop it off or slice it off in order to be
able to get the wine out or things like that, or figs
or or who knows what.
Okay. So אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Pappa, רב פפא Rav Pappa
says, עובדי כוכבים אדנא, ovdei kochavim adana, now a new case. So
in other words, we sort of seem to have resolved this case.
רב פפא Rav Pappa had given his ruling and רב יימר Rav
Yeimar says, "Oh, it's כתנאי, ke-tanna'ei, it's like this opinion of רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda in a case about טומאה." tumah. So this is
an interesting association. We've connected the laws of יין נסך yayin nesech
with the laws of טומאה, tumah, that is the kind of contact
that a person would have to have in order to disqualify something
because of טומאה tumah in the Tannaitic period is now being associated
by an אמורא Amora to a case of יין נסך. yayin nesech.
So it's an interesting association.
Okay, another case of רב פפא. Rav Pappa. We'll see רב פפא
Rav Pappa and his family feature rather prominently on today's דף. daf.
Yup. Back to the תרומה terumah thing. So this is only going
to apply, this is only going to apply תרומה. terumah. מעשר שני,
ma'aser sheni, it wouldn't apply because
מעשר שני ma'aser sheni would only go up to שני. sheni. Yeah,
right. So it won't be a problem. So for, and it could
be קודש kodesh wine or something like that, much less common. קודש,
kodesh, I believe, you need it for the בית המקדש Beit Ha-Mikdash
for נסכים nesachim or something. Yeah, right. Much less common. Okay. אמר
רב
פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, עובדי כוכבים אדנא וישראל אקובא. ovdei kochavim adana
ve-Yisrael akuba. What happens if the non-Jewish person is pouring, you go
to the wine store, and the way they had wine wholesalers back
then was you would have like, keep my same barrel here. So
they would have, you would, you would pour out the wine from
the thing and then you would have a smaller, you can be
very artsy here, they would have one of these,
okay,
and you would pour the wine into here. So the person buying
the wine is going to hold a flask like this and the
person pouring the wine is tilting the big barrel, okay? So this
is the אדנא adana and this is the קובא, kuba, okay?
So עובדי כוכבים אדנא, ovdei kochavim adana, if the idol worshipper, the
non-Jew is tilting the big barrel, וישראל אקובא, ve-Yisrael akuba, and the
ישראל Yisrael is holding the smaller flask, חמרא אסיר, chamra asir, the
wine is prohibited. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? כי קאתי מכח עובדי כוכבים
קאתי. ki ka-ati mi-koach ovdei kochavim ka-ati. The wine is being poured
because of the strength, because of the force of the non-Jew. The
non-Jewish person is in control of the flow of the wine because
he's tilting the barrel. וישראל אדנא, ve-Yisrael adana, and if in the
case that the Jewish person is tilting the large barrel, ועובדי כוכבים
אקובא, ve-ovdei kochavim akuba, and the עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim is holding
the flask stationary, חמרא שרי, chamra shari, the wine will be permissible.
But ואי מצדדי צדודי, ve-im mi-tzadadi tzedudi, if he tilts it around,
אסיר, asir, it will be prohibited. Why? The point is that if
you're just holding it stationary, you're not actually doing anything. There's no
action that the non-Jew is taking. So holding the קובא kuba is
not problematic.
And as רש״י Rashi says, קובא... kuba... no, that's going to come
up later. Sorry.
Yeah.
Fine. Okay.
Okay, so that's the next case. That is in other words, just
holding stationary is not going to be a problem.
Okay. איבעיא להו: צדורי אסור? Ibaya lehu: tzidure asur? אמר רב
פפא: Amar Rav Pappa: האי עובד כוכבים דדרי זיקא וכאזיל ישראל אחוריה
Hai oved kochavim d'dari zika v'kazil Yisroel achorei. What about a case
of a non-Jewish person is transporting wine in a wine skin, in
a bag, and the Jewish person is following after them? So in
the case that is to make sure that they don't do any
nefarious, idolatrous things with the wine. Okay. So מליא malya if it's
full of wine,
שרי shari דלא מקרקש. d'lo mekarkesh. חסירא chasira אסור asur דילמא מקרקש.
dilma mekarkesh. So if it was full, it's permissible because you can't
shake it around. There's no air bubble, so there's no shaking, so
it doesn't, there you can't do anything to it. But if it's
partially empty, then you could shake it around and that's what makes
it prohibited. Okay. Okay.
קובה Kuba מליא malya אסור asur but if it's an open amphora,
an open jar like this, it's prohibited even if it's full, דילמא
נגע dilma naga because maybe he would have touched it because the
wine reaches near the top of the flask. חסירא chasira but if
it's only partially full, שרי shari דלא נגע. d'lo naga. It becomes
permissible because it's partially empty and he couldn't reach. So that is
if you have wine in a, in a, now I can't, I
can't draw a difference between a jar here. This is a jar,
okay, and this is a bag, right? So if here it's only
full partially, then this is אסור asur and here if it's only
full partially,
this will be מותר. mutar. Okay, because here he can't touch it,
and here he could shake it around, right? So those are the
differences. Okay.
Okay. Fine. What about רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, רב אשי
Rav Ashi disagrees with רב פפא Rav Pappa and says זיקא zika
a wine skin, if it's in a bag it's not in a
jar, בין מליא ובין חסירא שרי. bein malya u'bein chasira shari. If
it's full or empty, it's permissible. מאי טעמא? Mai tama? אין דרך
ניסוך בכך. Ein derech nisuch b'kach. That's not the way people perform
idolatrous worship to use wine that's being transported in a wine skin,
in a bag. The notion that the wine would be carried in
a skin, I think, is generally lesser,
less preservation of the quality of the wine and it's less כבוד
kavod in some way. It's sort of a cheaper implement. So there's
a sense that it's not going to be done in an appropriate
way or that's not the way that they normally worship their idols
or something like that to use it from a bag.
It's like ניסוך nisuch from a beer can.
That's right. Something like that. It's like clearly more of a disposable
container.
Okay.
So in the previous case, are we concerned that the non-Jew, if
he was pouring the wine for the Jew, that in that process
he was making some kind of an idolatrous...?
I don't think necessarily. I think we're concerned that the דרבנן d'rabbanan
rules of סתם יינם stam yeinam that he's having enough contact and
enough control over the wine, the flow of the wine, where it
is, it's like he's touching it enough that it's a problem, right?
Just like shaking the bottle is a problem, so here tilting the
barrel and pouring it out is also a problem, even if he's
not, even if you could be 100% sure he doesn't have any
religious intent.
So then what would we say the problem was if we're sure
it's not religious? The contact with a non-Jew and wine and socialization
and all this?
Yes, things like that. I mean that may have been the motivation
behind making the law, but at the end of the day, they
made a law that non-Jews handling wine
isn't allowed.
Right. Okay. אין דרך ניסוך בכך. Ein derech nisuch b'kach. Okay.
מאצרא זיירא. Me'atzra zeira. So what are we talking about? So to
talk about the wine press, in the wine press. So רב פפי
שרי, Rav Pappi shari, רב פפי Rav Pappi allows it. רב אשי
ואיתימא רב שימי בר אשי אסור. Rav Ashi v'isima Rav Shimi bar
Ashi asur. And רב שימי בר אשי Rav Shimi bar Ashi says
it's not allowed. So what are we really talking about? The גמרא
Gemara is not so clear. Okay. So if you look at
רש"י, Rashi, מאצרא זיירא, Me'atzra zeira, גת שאין דורכין אלא כופשין בקורה.
gat she'ein dorechin ela kofshin bakora. It's a wine press where they
don't press the grapes with their feet, but they use a mechanical
press. Okay. So we put the grapes into this thing. We have
a piston type device and there is a beam and you push
up here, this pushes down, crushes the grapes and the wine flows
out. Okay. That's what we're talking about. That is if the non-Jew
is operating the press in a way in which they don't actually
have any contact with the grapes directly. Right? We already talked about
if the non-Jewish person is actually touching the grapes with their feet
or with their hands, or... Whatever, but what about here, we're talking
about in a case where there was no physical contact with the
grapes and the wine themselves. Okay. So, Rav Pappi or maybe it's
Rav Pappa, it's a little bit unclear,
says that it's permissible and Rav Ashi or perhaps Rav Shimi bar
Ashi says it's not permissible. So בכוחו, bekocho, if it was being
done by his own action, by his own strength. Okay. בכוחו כולי
עלמא לא פליגי דאסור. bekocho kulei alma lo peligi de'asur. Everyone will
agree that it is prohibited because if the non-Jewish person is the
one who's control has the force, has the power over the wine,
then that would be what's prohibited. That's like tilting the barrel. Okay.
כי פליגי בכוח כוחו. ki peligi bekoach kocho. But the debate is
what about a secondary degree of control or power? And look at
רש״י: Rashi: כוח כוחו כגון שמגלגל והגלגל קורי ויץ והוא מפלת הקורה
בלשון לעז. koach kocho kegon shemegalgel vehagalgal korei vaitz vehu mapelet hakorah
belashon laz. So if you actually just press, I take my arm
and I press the lever and it crushes the grapes, that's בכוחו.
kocho. That's my strength is controlling the wine press and that's going
to be a problem. But if I put rocks into the thing
and the rocks weigh it down and that's what does it, so
it's not בכוחו, kocho, then that's בכוח כוחו. koach kocho. The action
is being effected by a secondary action undertaken by the non-Jewish person
and the debate of these אמוראים amoraim is about בכוח כוחו. koach
kocho. Do we are we concerned about a secondary degree of control?
Okay. כי פליגי, ki peligi, okay,
איכא דאמרי בכוח כוחו כולי עלמא לא פליגי דשרי. ika de'amri bekoach
kocho kulei alma lo peligi deshari. But there's a second version of
how to treat this debate that we actually could say, no, really
everyone agrees that בכוח כוחו koach kocho is permissible. לא פליגי דשרי.
lo peligi deshari. כי פליגי בכוחו. ki peligi bekocho.
And actually the debate between Rav Pappi and Rav Ashi is about
בכוחו kocho directly, meaning even if if there's no contact at all
and it's just a matter of your force creating the wine, even
there maybe that's actually even the debate. And בכוח כוחו, koach kocho,
two degrees removed, I'm putting the rocks into the basket to weigh
down the wine press, that's going to be everyone would agree that
that's permissible. Okay. So הוה עובדא בכוח כוחו. hava uvda bekoach kocho.
The case, a case presented itself that was a case of בכוח
כוחו, koach kocho, secondary degree, ואסר רב יעקב מנהר פקוד. ve'asar Rav
Yaakov minahar pekod. And Rav Yaakov from מנהר פקוד nahar pekod said
it was prohibited, which seemingly fits the first version and fits
the position of Rav Ashi within the first version. And we use
that as a מעשה רב, ma'aseh rav, a real case to try
to sort of prove that actually Rav Ashi's position as treated in
the first case was the was the הלכה. halacha. Yeah.
This would have application today where we use automated means of crushing
grapes.
Certainly. If there's a mechanical press which is powered by hydraulics or
powered by an electric motor or something like that, it may not
even be בכוח כוחו, koach kocho, meaning, and again, this has implications
both ways. If we want to say that, you know like I
was talking about the other day, Welch's grape juice or whatever, if
let's assume everything is totally automated, the grapes come in on a
conveyor belt dry, and they get dumped into a machine and they're
crushed by a robot and they get bottled. Okay. So if all
of that process is fully automated, you have a hard time saying
it's prohibited. If there's a step where someone is pressing a button
or turning some lever or something like that, you get into בכוח
כוחו koach kocho questions.
And there's something else I was going to say about that. Oh,
but the opposite problem, פסח Pesach is coming, we have to talk
about machine מצות matzos or machine-made ציצית tzitzis or any other kind
of מצוה mitzvah item which needs to be done לשמה, lishmah, needs
to be done with כוונה, kavanah, needs to be done לשם מצוה,
leshem mitzvah, things like that. So can that be done by an
automated process? The question of machine מצות matzos in particular, when the
מצות-baking matzah machines came out in the 19th century, was a major
debate.
Can can you use such מצות matzos for the מצוה mitzvah of
מצה? matzah? Do they have the necessary human intent or not? Is
pressing a button that starts a run that makes 10,000 מצות matzos
good enough?
So there where a leniency in one place could bring a stringency
in another.
Certainly, certainly, in
which way you rule.
It always happens like that. Okay, you just have to know enough
cases to know which case is which. Okay. So right at the
bottom of ס׳ עמוד א׳, Samech Amud Aleph, ההוא חביתא דאיתקבא לאורכא.
hahu chavita
de'itka'a le'orka.
A case of a wine barrel that split lengthwise. So lengthwise means
use the same barrel, split lengthwise, it's got a crack running down
lengthwise. Okay.
So דאיתקבא לאורכא. de'itka'a le'orka. אתא ההוא עובד כוכבים חבקה.
ata hahu oved
kochavim chavkah. The non-Jew saw the wine is going to spill out,
he got he wanted to be a good Samaritan, quite literally,
and he jumps up and he hugs the wine barrel to keep
it closed so the wine doesn't spill out.
So. Okay, but a different version is that maybe it wasn't רפרם
בר פפא Rafram bar Papa and he was שרי, sharei, he allowed
them to drink it, but maybe it was רב הונא Rav Huna
the son of רב יהושע Rav Yehoshua and he allowed them only
לזבוני l'zavuney to sell it to non-Jews. You've seen this distinction for
the past few days that there may be some cases where it's
permissible to sell it but not permissible to drink it yourself.
And we're going to see actually in the next משנה Mishnah the
position of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon gets praised
for not having this intermediate category because it seems a little bit
ambiguous. Well, is it יין נסך yayin nesech or not? Like, just
tell me. But that also feeds into, like I had mentioned the
other day, the debate in the ראשונים Rishonim about maybe סתם יינם
stam yeinam that's only דרבנן de-Rabbanan or at least certain types of
סתם יינם stam yeinam that are only אסור מדרבנן assur mi-de-Rabbanan are
only permissible to drink and not to derive benefit from. But that's
an extensive debate. Okay. והני מילי דפקה לאורכה. ve-hanei milei d'faka l'orcha.
This is only in a case where it was split lengthwise. אבל
לפותיה aval l'futyeh but if it was split horizontally,
equatorially around the barrel, okay, אפילו
בשתייה שרי afilu bi-shtiyah sharei then even רב הונא Rav Huna the
son of רב יהושע Rav Yehoshua will allow you to drink the
wine. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason? מעשה לבנה קא עביד.
ma'aseh leveinah ka avid. You're,
the non-Jew is doing the work of a brick. That is what?
Here to provide the pressure to close the crack,
the longitude crack... sorry... the longitudinal crack...
the non-Jew has to be applying force from both sides, okay, to
close the crack. So he's really doing something to keep it from
pouring out of the crack. If it's split horizontally and he just
presses down, well he's doing מעשה לבנה, ma'aseh leveinah, he's doing the
same work that could be done by putting a brick on top.
That is, you're not doing anything. You're just applying pressure. Applying pressure
doesn't count as touching the wine. But here, sort of holding the
whole barrel closed
is maybe an artificial distinction but the difference between a vertical pressure
which could be done by an inanimate object and this horizontal pressure
which would be harder to set up a circumstance where it would
be done, especially in the ancient world, to do something horizontal requires
sort of the human action of holding it from both sides. חבקה,
chavkah, he was hugging it. Okay. ההוא עובד כוכבים דאשתכח דהוה קאי
במעצרתא. ha-hu oved kochavim d'ishtakach d'hava ka'ei be-ma'atzarta. They found a non-Jew
in the winepress. ואמר רב אשי, ve-amar Rav Ashi, אי איכא טופח
להטפיח ee eeka tfo'ach l'hatpi'ach if it was wet enough to be
able to wet something else, that's a common measure of moisture in
הלכה. halacha. It's wet enough that if you touch something else it
makes it wet. So בעי הדחה ובעי ניגוב, ba'ei hadachah ve-ba'ei niggub,
it has to be washed out and it has to then be
dried out afterward. ואי לא, ve-ee lo, and if it wasn't that
wet, it was only a little bit wet, בהדחה בעלמא סגי ליה.
be-hadachah b'alma sagi leh. That's good enough to just wash it out
without having to dry it out. Why? Because what's the problem? You
have to wash it out to get all of the יין נסך
yayin nesech off and you have to dry it up because whatever
יין נסך yayin nesech was there will be in the washing water.
So you have to get that out too. But if the amount
was a minimal amount, it needs to be diluted let's say but
it doesn't need to be washed off and with the wash water
totally removed.
Okay. What happens if a non-Jew takes a rope and puts it
around the cask that is splitting?
That's a good question. It seems to me like in such a
case the rope is doing the work, not the non-Jew. It sounds
like, now but again if he's the one tightening the rope or
something like that it would be the same thing. But it's an
interesting question because there it becomes a step removed. I wonder if
that's addressed by any of the ראשונים. Rishonim. It certainly seems like
a good question to ask.
I like that question. Okay, so we're at the next משנה Mishnah
on ס עמוד ב. samech amud bet. עובד כוכבים שנמצא עומד בצד
הבור של יין.
oved kochavim she-nimtza omed be-tzad ha-bor
shel yayin. A non-Jew was standing next to the storage pit of
the wine. אם יש לו מלווה עליו אסור. im yesh lo milveh
alav assur. If he has a debt that he can collect against
this Jewish owner, then the wine is prohibited. Okay. אין לו מלווה
עליו מותר, ein lo milveh alav mutar, but if there is no
debt owed to him, then it's permissible. Okay, we're going to see
it's discussed in the גמרא Gemara a little bit, but basically the
assumption is if he has a debt he'll be able... he thinks
that this wine is collateral enough for him that he could touch
it, he could take it, he could drink it, he could do
whatever. נפל לבור, nafal la-bor, if someone fell into the pit, a
non-Jewish person fell into the storage pit, ועלה, ve-alah, and got back
out again. We're going to see this comes up again in the
גמרא Gemara as well, a little bit morbid. מדדו בקנה, medado be-kaneh,
or he measured it with a measuring rod. התיז את הצרעה בקנה,
hetiz et ha-tzirah be-kaneh, or he removed a wasp with a
rod. Or he was wiping the foam off the top of a
barrel that had a lot of foam. וכל אלו היה מעשה Vechol
elu hayah ma'aseh in all of those cases, it was a real
case that was presented, so those what, four cases, ואמרו ימכר ve'amru
yimacher and they said you should sell the wine. ורבי שמעון מתיר
Verabi Shimon matir and Rabbi Shimon said it's permissible, permissible seemingly even
to drink the wine. נטל את החבית וזרקה בחמתו לבור, Natal et
hachavit vezarkah bachemato labor, a non-Jewish person picked up a barrel of
wine and was very angry and threw the wine into the storage
pit, זה היה מעשה, zeh hayah ma'aseh, that was a real case
והכשירו vehichshiro and they permitted it, or he permitted it, maybe it's
Rabbi Shimon. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel,
והוא שיש לו מלווה על אותו יין. vehu sheyesh lo milveh al
oto yayin. Shmuel says it's not enough that the, or it's not
enough of a problem if the non-Jew has a debt against this
Jewish owner, he has to use the wine itself as a collateral.
Okay, because the assumption can't be the non-Jew is just going to
come and and do whatever he wants to your property, or maybe
that was the assumption in Mishnayic times, but by Shmuel's time the
sense was no, no, no, he'll only, there's only a risk of
him handling the wine if he thinks that that wine is actually
his collateral for this loan that he's going to come and mishandle
it. Okay. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, מתניתין נמי דייקא, matnitin
nami dika, the phrasing of the משנה Mishnah is very precise. דתנן,
Detnan, to compare to this משנה, Mishnah, המטהר יינו של עובדי כוכבים,
hametaher yeino shel ovdei kochavim, a person who wanted to purify the
wine of an עובדי כוכבים. ovdei kochavim. That means he wanted to
produce kosher wine for a non-Jewish owner. So how does a Jewish
person set up a circumstance to produce kosher wine for a non-Jewish
owner? The non-Jewish owner, you write a deal, right? You sign a
contract that says I'm going to pay you this much money if
you let me use your wine press and your grapes and your
whatever, and then I'll come collect the wine when it's all
fermented. Right, a kosher run in the factory, right? The Jew doesn't
have the facilities, he doesn't have the fruit, he has the money.
So he says, I'll pay you, but I have to bring in
Jewish workers. Okay. So that was the deal. So המטהר יינו של
עובדי כוכבים hametaher yeino shel ovdei kochavim ונותנו ברשותו venotno birshuto and
he left it in his possession. והלה כותב לו התקבלתי vehala kotev
lo hitkabalti and he writes, the non-Jew writes a שטר shtar that
says התקבלתי hitkabalti ממך מעות, mimcha ma'ot, I've already received the payment
from you, this is even though he didn't actually yet receive the
payment, מותר. mutar. At that point, there's no longer a risk that
the non-Jew will mishandle the wine because he wrote a שטר shtar
that says he already received the money. That's enough, it's out of
his mind enough that we're not worried he's going to come handle
the wine. אבל אם ירצה ישראל להוציאו Aval im yirtzeh Yisrael lehotzi'o
ואין מניחו עד שיתן לו מעות, ve'ein menicho ad sheyiten lo ma'ot,
but even if after he wrote the התקבלתי, hitkabalti,
if the Jew wants to go get the wine, he doesn't allow
him to עד שיתן לו מעות ad sheyiten lo ma'ot until he
actually pays the money,
זה היה מעשה בבית שאן zeh hayah ma'aseh beVeit She'an ואסרו. ve'asru.
They, they said the wine was prohibited. טעמא דאין מניחו, Ta'ama de'ein
menicho, the reason why is because he wouldn't let the Jew go
get the wine, so it sounded like he was keeping it for
himself, so he was willing to handle it, he thought of it
as his.
הא מניחו Ha menicho שרי, shari, it would have been permissible. שמע
מינה Shema mina מלווה על אותו יין בעינן milveh al oto yayin
ba'inan שמע מינה. shema mina. That is, רב אשי Rav Ashi used
this משנה Mishnah from further on, the next
משנה, Mishnah, in order to prove that שמואל's Shmuel read of our
משנה Mishnah is correct. So it's actually a very nice idea that
is even a משנה Mishnah from the same פרק, perek, the next
משנה Mishnah gives enough information for us to be able to figure
out maybe a detail of how one of the אמוראים Amoraim said
oh, שמואל Shmuel just sort of said, oh this משנה Mishnah must
be referring to such
a
case שיש לו מלווה על אותו יין, sheyesh lo milveh al oto
yayin, that he had the debt, that the collateral for the loan
was this wine specifically. And then רב אשי Rav Ashi comes and
uses the next משנה Mishnah to explain well why is it that
שמואל Shmuel explained it that way, it's because there's all of this
material.
Okay. נפלה לבור ועלה. Nafela labor ve'alah. So what about the case
of he fell into the wine pit and then he got out
again? So אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Pappa, רב פפא Rav Pappa
said לא שנו אלא שעלה מת, lo shanu ella she'ala met, it
only is permissible if he fell in and drowned in the wine
and and was removed dead. It’s very interesting grammatically, the עלה ala
I would think means he got out, not he was taken out,
it could have been העלוהו he'eluhu
or that he resurfaced,
well, something like that, but anyway, אבל עלה חי, aval ala chai,
if he emerged alive, אסור, assur, then it's prohibited. So מאי טעמא?
mai ta'ama? Oh, what’s the reasoning? אמר רב פפא amar Rav Pappa
דדמי עליה כיום אידם dedami alei k'yom edam because in a circumstance
where your life was in danger, you were gonna drown in this
barrel of wine and then you emerged safely, so immediately the non-Jewish
person is gonna have intense gratitude for having been saved from this
dangerous situation and he’ll want to pour out a libation to his
idol or whatever, and certainly it’s like יום אידם yom edam in
that it’s a day that he considers a celebratory day for his
holiday, we wouldn’t be allowed to do business with him as well.
Okay. מדדו בקנה כל אלו היה מעשה ואמר ימכר ורבי שמעון מתיר.
madedo bekaneh kol elu hayah ma'aseh ve'amar yimacher ve'Rabbi Shimon matir. So
the מחלוקת machloket in the משנה Mishnah was that the חכמים Chachamim
or the anonymous משנה Mishnah seems to say that these are prohibited
for a Jewish person to drink, but you could sell them, and
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it’s permissible seemingly even to drink. So
אמר רב אדא בר אהבה, amar Rav Adda bar Ahava, רב אדא
בר אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava said ינוחו לו לרבי שמעון ברכות
על ראשו, yanuchu lo le'Rabbi Shimon brachot al rosho, there should be
many ברכות brachot on רבי שמעון'ס Rabbi Shimon's head, כשהוא מתיר מתיר
אפילו בשתייה, keshehu matir matir afilu bishtiya, if he says it’s allowed
then it’s really allowed, even to drink it, וכשהוא אוסר אוסר אפילו
בהנאה, u'keshehu osser osser afilu behana'ah, and when he says it’s prohibited,
he says it’s prohibited even to derive benefit from, that is, he’s
unambiguous, he has only two categories, it’s מותר muttar to drink, it’s
מותר muttar to sell it, or it’s אסור assur to drink and
it’s אסור assur to sell it, but he doesn’t have this intermediate
category of מותר muttar to sell and אסור assur to drink. Okay,
so רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava likes that about
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, that is, he takes his position to the
fullest extent, he takes it seriously, he doesn’t have a gray zone
or intermediate category. Okay.
There’s a note here by רש"ש Rashash that says that blessing would
only be appropriate if רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon was still alive, so
he suggests there were two רב אדא בר אהבה'ס.
Rav Adda bar Ahavas. Right. I don’t know about that. Okay. It’s
an interesting suggestion from the רש"ש, Rashash, but I’m not sure. רב
אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava we know is one of
the אמוראים Amoraim and fine, so he could I mean, but they
also believe in עולם הבא, Olam Haba, why can't he have ברכות
על ראשו brachot al rosho ב'עולם הבא, be'Olam Haba, right? I'm not
sure. I’ll have to see the רש"ש Rashash inside. I’ll look into
the רש"ש. Rashash.
It’s תוספות Tosafot
in תענית Taanit says there were two scholars.
But תוספות Tosafot always says there are two people, right? תוספות Tosafot
also says that רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha are
two different people, right?
Sometimes, I mean sometimes to make certain גמרות Gemarot make sense, we
have different traditions about what someone said, so if they contradict then
you have to say either one of the traditions is wrong or
they're two different people. וכשהוא אוסר אוסר
אפילו בהנאה.
u'keshehu osser osser
afilu behana'ah. I have to tell my joke about the רש"ש Rashash
now. So the story goes, this is a real story as far
as I know, but it’s a funny story, which is that supposedly
רב שלמה זלמן אוירבך Rav Shlomo Zalman Auerbach was teaching a גמרא
שיעור Gemara shiur in his ישיבה, yeshiva, and at some point someone
mentioned to him or brought up during the שיעור, shiur, oh, you
know, I heard the only reason the רש"ש'ס Rashash's commentary is printed
in the back of the וילנא ש"ס Vilna Shas is because the
רש"ש'ס Rashash's father-in-law was very wealthy and paid a lot of money
for them to print the רש"ש Rashash in the in the גמרא
Gemara because he was roughly contemporary with the ראם Re'em family printing
house, and רב שלמה זלמן אוירבך Rav Shlomo Zalman Auerbach shot back
and said, I also would have spent a lot of money to
have the רש"ש Rashash printed in the וילנא ש"ס. Vilna Shas. רש"ש
Rashash
is very has very insightful and very original comments very often, and
certainly is always a good a good אחרון acharon to take a
look at.
I like the רש"ש Rashash a lot. Okay. אמר רבי חייא בריה
דאבא בר נחמני, amar Rabbi Chiyya brei de'Abba bar Nachmani, so רבי
חייא Rabbi Chiyya the son of אבא בר נחמני Abba bar Nachmani
says אמר רב חסדא אמר רב amar Rav Chisda amar Rav quoting
from רב חסדא Rav Chisda quoting רב, Rav, ואמרי לה אמר רב
חסדא אמר זעירי הלכה כרבי שמעון.
ve'amri lah amar
Rav Chisda amar Zeiri halacha ke'Rabbi Shimon. So they all these different
אמוראים Amoraim say they think הלכה halacha is like רבי שמעון'ס Rabbi
Shimon's opinion. איכא דאמרי אמר רב חסדא אמר לי אבא בר חנה
הכי אמר זעירי הלכה כרבי שמעון, ika de'amri amar Rav Chisda amar
li Abba bar Chana hachi amar Zeiri halacha ke'Rabbi Shimon, or the
third version of exactly how this tradition was passed on. However, the
גמרא Gemara concludes ואין הלכה כרבי שמעון. ve'ein halacha ke'Rabbi Shimon. In
fact, the final conclusion will not be like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
That is other אמוראים Amoraim wanted to consider that case, and specifically
we’re talking about those those four cases
where right, the he touched it with only with a measuring pole,
he was getting the fly out of the wine or whatever, he
didn't he didn't touch the wine, he didn't really move or stir
the wine anyway, right? He was either measuring the depth of the
wine... the wine, how much wine is there, he was taking a
hornet out, or he fell in by accident and died,
or he wiped the foam off the top of the barrel but
didn't actually touch the wine itself. So in all of those cases
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it's perfectly permissible and the רבנן Rabbanan
say that it's still prohibited because of יין נסך Yayin Nesekh but
you could sell it, so it's not אסור בהנאה, Assur Be-Hana'ah, and
all of these other אמוראים Amoraim wanted to say oh the הלכה
Halakha should be like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and still we say
no. Generally, it's a rare case where we say the הלכה Halakha
follows רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon opinion. I mean certain cases certainly and
again certain other תנאים, Tannaim, but generally like if he's in a
debate with רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda usually the הלכה Halakha follows רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, not always.
Yes, Charlie.
ArtScroll says there's this מחלוקת Machloket רמב״ם Rambam and ראב״ד Ra'avad where
ראב״ד Ra'avad actually holds like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
Because probably he has some other version of the גמרא Gemara or
he reads it differently or he has some other סוגיא. Sugya. I
have to see inside and take a look at the ראב״ד. Ra'avad.
Which
פרק? Perek? ספר קדושה,
Sefer
Kedusha,
הלכות מאכלות אסורות, Hilkhot Ma'akhalot Assurot, which פרק? Perek?
פרק Perek 12. 12.
Okay, so I'll take a look after the שיעור, Shiur, that's a
good thing to know.
Okay. The next piece is about the throwing. Okay? So right, the
last case in the משנה Mishnah had been, right, if he threw
the wine barrel into the wine storage pit, זה היה מעשה Ze
Hayah Ma'aseh and he was angry, right? זרקה בחמתו, Zaraka Be-Hamato, he
threw it while he was angry. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says:
נטל החבית וזרקה בחמתו לבור זה היה מעשה והכשירו, Natal He-Havit Ve-Zaraka
Be-Hamato La-Bor Ze Hayah Ma'aseh Ve-Hikhshiru, they said it was permissible. אמר
רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, רב אשי Rav Ashi says: כל שבזב
טמא, Kol She-Be-Zav Tameh, an idea which we already saw earlier a
little bit, so whatever kind of contact would be considered to transfer
the impurity for someone who is a זב, Zav, בעובד כוכבים עושה
יין נסך. Be-Oveid Kokhavim Oseh Yayin Nesekh. Then if a non-Jewish person
does that to wine, then just like if a זב Zav will
make it טמא Tameh to transfer the impurity, if a non-Jewish person
does it to the wine it makes it יין נסך. Yayin Nesekh.
What's interesting about this we see many places where עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah and also עובדי עבודה זרה Ovdei Avodah Zarah are associated with
a certain level of טומאה. Tumah. Already in the time of the
תנאים, Tannaim, the משנה Mishnah in שבת Shabbat discusses the fact that
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah itself, idols, are מטמא כשרץ. Metamei Ke-Sheretz. They're
considered to be like like a dead dead lizard and things like
that.
וגם כתבי קודש.
Ve-Gam Kitvei Kodesh. And also that for a different reason and in
a different degree, not like a שרץ. Sheretz.
They're only מטמא את הידיים. Metamei Et Ha-Yadayim.
But so that's one instance. The Rabbis also instituted that even though
from תורה Torah law non-Jewish people do not, while they are alive
at least, do not become impure cannot transmit impurity, the Rabbis decreed
that all non-Jewish people be treated at the level of impurity of
a זב Zav or זבה. Zavah.
So here too the comparison between a זב Zav and an עובד
כוכבים Oveid Kokhavim is actually very comparable in a certain degree, which
is that the level of impurity which this non-Jewish person we assume
will transmit to the wine anyway, well he's also going to make
it not just טמא Tameh but also prohibited to derive any benefit
from it. Okay. So כל שבזב טהור בעובד כוכבים אינו עושה יין
נסך. Kol She-Be-Zav Tahor Be-Oveid Kokhavim Eino Oseh Yayin Nesekh. And if
it would remain pure while a זב Zav did it, then it
should not make יין נסך. Yayin Nesekh. So what was the case?
The case was someone threw a barrel of wine, he was very
angry, he picked up a barrel of wine and threw it into
the pit of wine. So wait a second,
if a זב Zav did that, would it be טהור Tahor or
טמא? Tameh? טהור. Tahor.
Why? That's what I didn't know why, because it doesn't you don't
spread טומאה Tumah by throwing.
By throwing, right. If he touched it, it's one thing. But if
he throws something into something else... okay, so let's see. So איתיבי
רב הונא לרב אשי, Itvei Rav Huna Le-Rav Ashi, רב הונא Rav
Huna challenged רב אשי's Rav Ashi position: נטל החבית וזרקה בחמתו לבור
זה היה מעשה בבית שאן והכשירו. Natal He-Havit Ve-Zaraka Be-Hamato La-Bor Ze
Hayah Ma'aseh Be-Veit Sh'an Ve-Hikhshiru. So רב הונא Rav Huna challenged רב
אשי's Rav Ashi statement by quoting our משנה Mishnah and said our
משנה Mishnah seems like a proof against you because our case is
a case of throwing something and it said והכשירו. Ve-Hikhshiru. So we
can infer from the משנה: Mishnah: בחמתו אין, Be-Hamato In, the only
reason it's permissible is because he was angry is why he threw
it. That is he did it without any כוונה. Kavanah. However, שלא
בחמתו, She-Lo Be-Hamato, if he did it while he was not angry,
when he was calm and his intent was to throw the wine
into the pit, לא, Lo, it would be prohibited. So
how can רב אשי Rav Ashi defend his general principle? It sounds
like our משנה Mishnah contradicts it. So what do we have to
do? We have to reinterpret the word זרקה לבור, Zaraka La-Bor, threw
it into the pit. And how do we interpret instead? התם דקאזיל
מיניה ומיניה, Hatam De-Ka'azil Minei U-Minei, it was actually not throwing, it
was something more along the lines of rolling. But רש״י Rashi says
דקאזיל מיניה ומיניה, De-Ka'azil Minei U-Minei, שהוליך ומתגלגל הכלי כל שעה על
ידי שהוא מגלגלו ומורידו לבור. She-Holikh U-Mitgalgel Ha-Kli Kol Sha'ah Al Yedei
She-Hu Megalgelo U-Morido La-Bor. It's like rolling it into the pit. הלכך
שלא בחמתו לא דחיישינן דילמא נגע. Hilkhakh She-Lo Be-Hamato Lo De-Haishinan Dilma
Naga. We're concerned that when he finally lowered it into the pit
when it rolled to the edge and rolled in, that he actually
touched the wine that was in the pit. But the kind of
contact he would have had from throwing is
not. What happened? It happened, they're describing a case that actually happened,
right? What does the משנה mishnah actually say? The משנה mishnah actually
says, right? נטל החבית וזרקה בחמתו לבור. Natol ha-chavit ve-zarkah b-chamato la-bor.
He picked it up and threw it because he was angry, right?
זה היה מעשה והכשירו. Zeh hayah ma'aseh ve-hekhshiru. It was the case.
So רב הונא Rav Huna and רב אשי Rav Ashi inferring, right,
really רב הונא, Rav Huna, inferring from the משנה, mishnah, oh, the
only reason the משנה mishnah has to teach me the word בחמתו
be-chamato that he was angry, I can implicitly understand from our משנה
mishnah that had he not been angry they would not have allowed
it. But
that's not necessarily true at all. That's not a very sharp read
of the משנה. mishnah.
It's taking a lot of what the אמוראים amora'im very often do
with משניות mishnayot is a hyper-literalism. They or omni-significance. Every little word
in the משנה mishnah is of legal significance. So not just describing
the case, oh it was an angry guy. The fact that he
was angry when he threw the barrel must mean his level of
intent was important for the determination of whether or not the wine
would be kosher in that circumstance. It's actually fascinating to see that
they take this omni-significant read of the משנה, mishnah, infer a הלכה
halakhah which seemingly contradicts the conclusion of the משנה mishnah in order
to either challenge or challenge רב אשי Rav Ashi's general rule. And
then what does רב אשי Rav Ashi do? רב אשי Rav Ashi
has to even further stretch the משנה mishnah to fit his rule,
right? He reinterprets: oh, he didn't throw it into the pit, he
really rolled it, right? So it's fascinating to see how much later,
you know, generations later the אמוראים amora'im working with משניות mishnayot that
already existed had to work to either because they had created sort
of more general rules or because they had different traditions or because,
you know, they wanted to read the משנה mishnah with that level
of omni-significance
that it would go to that extent. So we'll start tomorrow שבת,
Shabbat, we'll start with the next משנה mishnah on the top of
ס"א ע"א. Samech Aleph Amud Aleph. I hope everyone has a wonderful
שבת, Shabbat, שבת ראש חודש, Shabbat Rosh Chodesh, שבת החודש, Shabbat HaChodesh,
three ספרי תורה, sifrei Torah, there's a מנהג minhag in some communities
to have just as many קוגל kugel as you have ספרי תורה,
sifrei Torah, so it's a three קוגל kugel שבת. Shabbat. I hope
everyone enjoys nice long דאוונען, davenning, הלל, Hallel, מוסף Musaf etc.